Guide to the Morris Bishop papers,1901-1974.
Bishop, Morris papers, 1901-1974.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Morris Bishop papers, 1901-1974.
14-18-641
Morris, Bishop 1893-1973.
17.5 cubic ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts, lecture notes, printed material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, research material, and manuscript drafts of Bishop's writings, particularly his A HISTORY OF CORNELL. Includes subject files, course lecture notebooks and notes, poems, and other printed material. Major correspondents include Arthur L. Abelson, Romeyn Berry, Edwin G. Boring, Gilmore D. Clarke, Arthur H. Dean, E. B. White, Walter F. Willcox, Bernard Burgunder, Emile Caillet, David Daiches, Robertson Davis, Leon Edel, Charles Henry Hull, J. J. Jusserand, and Vladmir Nabokov. Letters received by Bishop containing anecdotes about Cornell history are numerous.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Morris Gilbert Bishop was Professor of Romance Literature, University Historian.
Class of 1913, M.A. 1914, Ph.D., 1926, Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, research material, and manuscript drafts of Bishop's writings, particularly his A HISTORY OF CORNELL. Includes subject files, course lecture notebooks and notes, poems, and other printed material. Major correspondents include Arthur L. Abelson, Romeyn Berry, Edwin G. Boring, Gilmore D. Clarke, Arthur H. Dean, E. B. White, Walter F. Willcox, Bernard Burgunder, Emile Caillet, David Daiches, Robertson Davis, Leon Edel, Charles Henry Hull, J. J. Jusserand, and Vladmir Nabokov. Letters received by Bishop containing anecdotes about Cornell history are numerous.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bishop, Morris,1893-1973.; Abelson, Arthur L.; Berry, Romeyn, 1881-1957.; Bishop, Morris, 1893-1973.; Boring, Edwin Garrigues, 1886-1968.; Burgunder, Bernard.; Caillet, Emile.; Clarke, Gilmore D., 1892-; Daiches, David, 1912-; Davies, Robertson, 1913-; Dean, Arthur H.(Arthur Hobson), 1898-1987.; Edel, Leon, 1907-; Hull, Charles Henry, b. 1864.; Jusserand, J. J.(Jean Jules), 1855-1932.; Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1899-1977.; White, E. B.(Elwyn Brooks), 1899-; Willcox, Walter Francis, 1861-1964.; Cornell University--History.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
There are also a number of Bishop manuscripts cataloged individually as call number PS3503.I79 ++. Related collection: Alison Mason Kingsbury papers, #3663.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Boxes 1-49
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Documents and Family Materials
Series IV. Photographs
Series V. Publications
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Boxes 1-49: A copy of the paper guide to this collection is available by clicking here. (1Morris Bishop PDF)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1944 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1945 (Box 52, Folder 2-3)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1946-1947 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1948-1949 (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1950-1952 (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1960-1961 (Box 52, Folder 7)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1927 (Box 52, Folder 8)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1928-1931 (Box 52, Folder 9)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1931-1937 (Box 52, Folder 10)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1938-1941 (Box 52, Folder 11)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1942-1943 (Box 52, Folder 12)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1943, 1961-1968 (Box 52, Folder 13)
  - Xerox copies of letters, Maurice Graham (Box 52, Folder 14)
  - Xerox copies of letters, 1963-1975 (Box 52, Folder 15)
  - Xerox Copies of Nabokov letters and item list (Box 52, Folder 16)
  - Two letters to Santa Claus, 1900 (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence about MB's publications mainly to Alison Mason Kingsbury, 1970s-1980s (Box 53, Folder 7)
  - Letters relating to Morris Bishop gifts to Cornell, circa 1970s (Box 53, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Athens to Keith Falkner at Cornell, 1951-52 (Box 53, Folder 13)
    letters sent to Alison Jolly by Julia Falkner also 1953 concert with Keith Falkner, Willard Straight hall
  - Portrait of Morris Bishop by Kenneth Evett with letter and article (Box 53, Folder 16)
  - copy of letter from Charles Nisbert to Lord Buchan, Oct 15th 1794 (Box 53, Folder 17)
    copy of letter from Charles nisbert, formerly of Montrose, Scotland from Carlisle, Pennsylvania, to his friend Lord Buchan in Edinburgh
  - Letters from Morris Bishop to grandmother Martha Gilbert, 1904-1920s (Box 53, Folder 20-22)
    mostly to aunt Marion Gilbert. Excerpted in 'I think I Have been here before'. Also two small people made of string
  - letters to Morris Bishop, 1907-1947 (Box 53, Folder 19)
    Includes letter from his daughter Alison Bishop with photographs, and loose landscape photographs
  - Marion E. Gilbert letters, circa 1960s (Box 54, Folder 21)
    letters
- Series III. Documents and Family Material
  - Extract from I think I have been here before, 1981 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - Copyrights of Morris Bishop's writings (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - List of books published and supporting contracts (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - Senior Year Book for Yonkers High School, 1909 (Box 53, Folder 4)
    Includes names of class and faculty members, edited by MB.
  - Small black address book, 1968 (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Two school exercise books, one for Bessie Gilbert, one for Morris Bishop which also contains drawings and photographs (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - MB's obituaries and who's who entry, 1973 (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - History of the Buccaneers of America, 1909 (Box 53, Folder 9)
    by James Burney, gift to Morris Bishop
  - Information on the Gilbert Geneologies (Box 53, Folder 10-12)
    contains letters, photos and family documents relating to family history
  - Morris Bishop Athens, 1951-52 (Box 53, Folder 13)
    notes for course of 'American Life and Civilization' Fulbright professorship, Athens, 'As if I'm supposed to teach civilization to the Greeks'
  - Morris Bishop miscellaneous, 1960-70s (Box 53, Folder 14)
  - The adventure of the Paralysed Canary, 1930s? (Box 53, Folder 15)
    Sherlock Holmes spoof
  - Canticle music score (Box 53, Folder 15)
    Morris Bishop left a small sum for an annual dinner of the romance language dept. of Cornell. He stipulated that they should chant the enclosed doggerel, later set to music by Prof. Alice Colby-Hall
  - A Song of Jocy, Warren Benson, Plymouth Music Co., Inc. (Box 53, Folder 15)
  - Sale of Vladimir Nabokov collection by Glen Horowitz (Box 53, Folder 18)
  - Morris Bishop notebook, 1907 (Box 53, Folder 23)
    with catechism answers and list of stocks held - only date 1907
  - wallet - Edwin Rubergall Bishop, Morris Bishop's father (Box 53, Folder 23)
    photo of ERB in uniform of Dufferin Rifles, Canada. ERB Naturalizaion USA certificate 1890 book of hand-copied uplifting quotes including Auinas and Danty. ERB draft will providing for guardianship and ducation of sons Morris and Edwin (Ted)
  - Cornell Athletics Membership tickets booklets, 1910-1914 (Box 54, Folder 12)
  - Historic Cornell postcards, 1911 (Box 54, Folder 12)
    Morris Bishop bought old unused postcards from 2nd hand shops and sent them to bewildered friends.
  - Bessie E Gilbert's diary, 1878-1886 (Box 54, Folder 13)
  - Original "Morris Bishop: Eighty Years" manuscript (Box 54, Folder 15-16)
  - Morris Bishop's souvenirs, 1950s -1977s (Box 54, Folder 17)
    Contains letters, cards, newpaper cuttings and other souvenirs
  - Morris Bishop's biographical material, 1893-1970s (Box 54, Folder 18)
    Contains newspaper cuttings, copies of will, letters.
  - Ted Bishop photographs and documents, circa 1914-1950s (Box 54, Folder 19)
  - John P. Gilbert will and letters, circa 1950s (Box 54, Folder 20)
    copy of will and letters
  - Morris Bishop Old light verse (Box 56, Folder 8)
  - Gilbert family documents, circa 1890-1920s (Box 55)
    Includes newspaper cuttings, diary, letters, address book and other documents, photos
  - Bishop Geneology, circa 1930s-60s (Box 57, Folder 2)
    mainly letters relating to family tree
  - Marriage Vow book, with baptism and confirmation certificates (Box 57)
  - Common Prayer book used by Edwin and Bessie Bishop (Box 57)
  - Morris Bishop's baby book (Box 62)
  - Two sashes worn by Erskine Mason, Alison Mason Kingsbury's grandfather (Box 62)
  - Doctoral Hoods, MU-944-947 (Box 58)
  - Hofstra diploma (Box 58)
  - Morris Bishop suitcase, MU-948
  - Pins and medallions, MU-2306-2346 (Box 59)
  - Fur regalia, MU-2347 (Box 60)
- Series IV. Photographs
  - Morris Bishop and Huntington club members, 1910-1913, 1960 (Box 53, Folder 24)
  - Dedication of Clark Hall, 1965 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - Bishop at dedication of Clark Hall, Cornell, 1965 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - Group at dinner at the Captain's table, De Grasse, setting out for Greece, 1952 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - Edith Fox, Morris Bishop and Alison Mason Kingsbury photo, 1965 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - Cornell group photo for dedication of plaque at apartment buildings, circa 1960s (Box 53, Folder 25)
    for dedication of plaque on the apartment buildings
  - Colgate - honorary PhD's, circa 1959 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - meeting of Canadian Library Association, 1950 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - class of 1914, 1964 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - portrait photo of Morris Bishop taken in the American Institute of Arts and letters, 1973 (Box 53, Folder 25)
    taken in the American Institute of Arts and letters
  - reproduction of oil portrait of Morris Bishop, 1930 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - photo of MB, AMK, Billy Gilbert and Rosette Hargrove, 1935 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - Morris Bishop with Mark Vandoren and John Holmes, circa 1960s (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - Morris Bishop and Alison Mason Kingsbury, circa 1960s (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - 40 years reunion, 1954 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - Morris Bishop portraits, 1940s-1960s (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - Morris Bishop giving a speech, 1952 (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - Pictures of Morris Bishop, 1920-1940s (Box 53, Folder 26)
  - Harriet Gilbert (Box 53, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous friends, circa 1880-1940 (Box 53, Folder 28)
  - Edwin and Morris, Betsy Childs, Francis Gilbert (Box 53, Folder 29)
  - Ethel Cooke, Susannah Farr Bishop, William Morris Gilbert Jr. (Box 53, Folder 30)
  - Ithaca scenery (Box 53, Folder 30)
  - Morris Bishop, circa 1900-1920 (Box 53, Folder 30)
  - Morris Bishop as a young man, circa 1910 (Box 54, Folder 1)
    various sizes
  - Morris Bishop, circa 1955 (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - portrait photo of Morris Bishop, 1963 (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Photos of Marion Gilbert, circa 1890s (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Bessie and Edward R. Bishop, 1890s (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Morris Bishop WWI and WWII photos, 1915-1945 (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Morris Bishop photos, 1960s-1970s (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Martha Bailey Gilbert (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Bailey, Cheeman, and Woodside relatives (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - May Bishop (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Edwin R. Bishop, 1870s-1890s (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Ted and Morris Bishop, Edwin G. Bishop, 1900s (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - Photos of Alison Mason Kingsbury and Morris Bishop, circa 1930s (Box 54, Folder 7)
  - Morris Job Gilbert, circa 1880-1901 (Box 54, Folder 8)
  - Ted and Morris Bishop, Edwin G. Bishop, 1890s-early 1900s (Box 54, Folder 9)
  - Marion E. Gilbert, 1878-ca.1900 (Box 54, Folder 10)
  - Little album from Yonker's House, with Edwin, May, and others, 1905 (Box 54, Folder 11)
  - Mary Nellis Bishop, Mary Bishop Farr, Lou Gilbert, Samuel Gilbert, Sarah Gilbert, "Bleak House" (Box 54, Folder 11)
  - Willard, NY photo postcards (Box 54, Folder 11)
  - John Parke Gilbert (Box 54, Folder 11)
  - Morris Bishop photos from Anner Weeks' desk, 1960s-1970s (Box 54, Folder 11)
  - Photos of Morris Bishop sent by Joan Gilbert Martin, 158 Belvedered Terrace Santa Cruz CA 95062 (Box 54, Folder 12)
    1. Morris Bishop: WW1 lieutenant. 2. Morris Bishop and unidentified friend in France, WW1. 3. Morris Bishop and French Railway, WW11. 4. House in Ithaca - not 903 Wyckof. 5. Clipping of Morris Bishop's brother Edwin G. Bishop (uncle Ted) City Clerk 1927.
  - Red foldout album with photos of Edwin R. Bishop and three others (Box 54, Folder 14)
  - Morris Bishop portraits, Alison Mason Kingsbury and Bishop (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - photo from a scene from a play, Ithaca, circa 1930 (Box 56, Folder 2)
    group photo dressed as angels?
  - May Bishop (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - large photo of MrsLivingston Farrand, 1946 (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - large portrait photo of Conway Todd (Box 56, Folder 3)
    architect of 903 Wyckoff Road, Ithaca
  - Morris Gilbert (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - Reverend William Morris Gilbert and family, circa 1865-1924 (Box 56, Folder 5-6)
  - collection of photos and negatives of Morris Bishop and Alison Mason Kingsbury, various (Box 56, Folder 7)
  - Frances Schultz (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - Framed photographs and dagguerotypes of various family members, 1860s-early 1900s (Box 61)
  - Two photographs of Morris Bishop, 1935 (Box 62)
  - Education and Social Economy Club, Panama International Exposition, 1915 (Map-case Folder 4)
- Series V. Publications
  - By Others
    - Cornell Faculty Memorial Statements, 1973-1974 (Box 52, Folder 17)
    - The Cornell Library Journal: Morris Bishop and Alison Mason Kingsbury bibliography- (Box 52, Folder 17)
    - Cornell Step Ahead, Olin Library Reader Report, 1971 (Box 52, Folder 17)